<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="page.xsl"?>
<page xmlns="http://benad.me/schema/page"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://benad.me/schema/page page.xsd">
    
    <!--
    Benad's Web Site by Benoit Nadeau is licensed under a Creative Commons
    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License
    https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/
    -->
    
    <head>
        <title>What I'm Not</title>
        <id>me_not</id>
    </head>
    <body>
        <section>
            <p>Before you jump to conclusions about who I am, I'd like to take
            some time to make sure I'm not incorrectly mislabelled as
            one of the following personality types.</p>
        </section>
        <section title="A Nerd">
            <p>I am not a "Nerd", that is someone obsessed with intellectualism.
            That is, even though I can quickly learn, I don't enjoy knowledge
            <i>per se</i>, nor pride myself for it.</p>
            <p>I don't enjoy reading books. I don't like remembering seemingly
            random facts. I don't like puzzles. And I <i>definitely</i> dislike
            chess.</p>
            <p>True, I may have some affinity with nerds, including being smart,
            slighly socially akwards and not liking sports (no, chess is
            <i>not</i> a sport). But having met and been friends with some
            <i>real</i> nerds many times, I can tell that there's still a
            difference between me and "them".</p>
            <p>I think one characteristic that I have and that few "proper"
            nerds don't have is that I am pragmatic. I don't learn something
            unless it can be useful through me or to teach to others. I find
            abstract thoughts and mind games absurd. I don't particularly like
            the idea of research in mathematics unless a specific potential
            application is thought of before hand.</p>
            <p>In a way, I may be a slightly "nerdy" engineer. Think of me of a
            non-<i>blasé</i> Dilbert.</p>
        </section>
        <section title="A Geek">
            <p>I am not a geek. That is, I don't particularly like any of the
            following:
                <html:ul>
                    <html:li>Star Trek</html:li>
                    <html:li>Star Wars</html:li>
                    <html:li>Almost all TV-based American science
                    fiction</html:li>
                    <html:li>Japanese animation, with a few exceptions</html:li>
                    <html:li>Lord of the Rings, and all its derivatives,
                    including World of Warcraft and most MMORPG</html:li>
                    <html:li>Most video games</html:li>
                </html:ul>
            </p>
            <p>And so on. True, I like gadgets <i>a bit</i>, but only as long
            as I actively
            use them. I like some science fiction. And some Japanese animation.
            And some video games. But let's be clear: I'm highly selective. Like
            everything else, 
            <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturgeon%27s_Law">90% of
            everything is crap</a>. And I'm not going to focus my attention
            only on things that make me escape from reality.</p>
        </section>
        <section title="An Apple Fan">
            <p>And I'm not an Apple fan. Yes, I own only Macs. And an Apple
            mouse. And an iPhone. And I prefer Macs. And a lot of Apple
            products.</p>
            <p>But let me be clear. Every day of work I make use of Mac, Windows
            and Linux at the same time. I can assemble a PC from parts and
            install Linux on it. I've been using Windows since Windows NT 4. I
            may generally dislike Microsoft Windows, but I often prefer using
            some Linux or Solaris distribution rather than Mac OS X. Most of the
            applications I use are 100% cross-platform. I dislike DRM, even
            when Apple-branded. I don't like how the iPhone platform is closed.
            I always prefer open-source over the amount of features and
            "support".</p>
            <p>I just prefer Macs in general, and don't mind paying for an
            extra bit of quality and warranty.</p>
            <p>And, really, Microsoft tends to annoy me in the way they make
            their software. At least with open-source I can fix it.</p>
        </section>
    </body>

</page>
